<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Python | Matthieu Pelissier</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/python/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/python/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Python</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://localhost:1313/media/icon_hu7729264130191091259.png</url>
      <title>Python</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/python/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Practical work in Python 3rd year</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/teaching/tpinfo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/teaching/tpinfo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Course Title:&lt;/strong&gt; Python for 3rd-Year Physics Students&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Duration:&lt;/strong&gt; 36 hours&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Topics Covered:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Core programming concepts: lists, strings, loops, functions, classes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Modules and libraries: NumPy, Matplotlib, SciPy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collaborative project work in the second half of the semester.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Teaching Methodology:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
The course combines guided lectures, notebook-based exercises, and interactive discussions. Students progressively work on group projects, fostering problem-solving and teamwork skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;evaluation-criteria&#34;&gt;Evaluation Criteria&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grades are based on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Performance in exercises.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Group project (code quality, report, and oral presentation).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;pedagogical-challenges&#34;&gt;Pedagogical Challenges&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introducing programming concepts to beginners.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Guiding group organization and dynamics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emphasizing scientific rigor in project development.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Illustrating the utility of simulations, and their exploitation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Addressing the integration of coding with/without LLM tools.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;personal-contributions&#34;&gt;Personal Contributions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond classroom instruction, my contributions include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enhancing Course Content:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Added corrections to notebook exercises.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introduced a section on efficient computation using NumPy (loop avoidance).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Designed a new notebook on the Pandas library for optional data analysis applications.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Support for Scientific Writing:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Developed a comprehensive introduction to LaTeX, enabling students to draft professional-quality reports despite prior unfamiliarity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Solving a differential equation for calibration of the ATLAS detector via a neural networks.</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/project/atlas/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/project/atlas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/project/atlas/distribution.jpg&#34;
    alt=&#34;Calibration Example: using neural network solution for ODE-based calibration function&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Calibration Example: using neural network solution for ODE-based calibration function&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Supervisor :&lt;/strong&gt; Pierre-Antoine Delsart, lecturer, ATLAS, LPSC, France.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The particle physics studied at the LHC by the ATLAS detector requires high-precision measurements.
precision. The energy quantities associated with hadronic jet objects cannot be used directly from experimental measurements, and must be corrected in order to be compared with theoretical predictions.
from experimental measurements, and must be corrected before they can be compared with theoretical predictions. This
addresses this problem in the form of a nonlinear second-order differential equation on the calibration function
function, which has no analytical solution. A neural network is used to solve it. The aim is to
is to obtain an accurate calibration function by exploiting the non-linear capabilities of neural networks.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Simulating bird flocking behavior - from simple rules to physical models</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/project/boids-simulation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/project/boids-simulation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/project/boids-simulation/boids.jpg&#34;
    alt=&#34;Example of a bird simulation using the rules of birds or the laws of physics. We can note the creation of groups for some parameters.&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Example of a bird simulation using the rules of birds or the laws of physics. We can note the creation of groups for some parameters.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Supervisor :&lt;/strong&gt; Mourad Ismaïl, Associate Professor in Applied Mathematics, LIPHY, Université Grenoble Alpes, France.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this project, we aimed to simulate bird swarms in a 2D infinite sky by using three simple rules proposed by Craig W. Reynolds in 1987. These rules, which are widely known as Boids, have been used in the cinema industry to simulate crowds. However, we wanted to model a system following physical laws to approach a collective bird behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We found that to effectively simulate physical rules with many parameters, it is necessary to use at least a fourth-order approximation method, such as the Runge-Kutta method. We can obtain a conservative system, where groups of birds/particles are formed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our simulations can be useful for studying systems where clusters appear from any distribution of constituents. However, we acknowledged that the model could still be improved by adding obstacles, fluid effects, a third dimension of space, or restricting the birds&amp;rsquo; field of vision to 180°.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, the understanding of collective behaviors is a scientific challenge that can be addressed by multiple disciplines such as biology, physics, and social sciences. By modeling the behavior of bird swarms, we can gain insights into how systems transition from a uniform state to swarm formations, which has practical applications in various fields.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Polarimetric signatures of accreting black holes</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/project/accretiondisk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Jul 2022 22:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/project/accretiondisk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/project/accretiondisk/BHimage.jpg&#34;
    alt=&#34;Model of a thick accretion disk around massive black holes, seen by an observer at infinity. The color refers to the synchrotron radiation produced with a vertical magnetic field.&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Model of a thick accretion disk around massive black holes, seen by an observer at infinity. The color refers to the synchrotron radiation produced with a vertical magnetic field.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Supervisor :&lt;/strong&gt; Dr. Alexandra Veledina, post-doctoral fellow ,Tuorla observatory, University of Turku, Finland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The black holes are compact celestial objects whose mass can be several times that of the sun. The gravity exerted is such that, from a certain surface called the event horizon, nothing can escape, not even light, which explains their name. Although it may seem paradoxical, it is possible to observe them. These objects are surrounded by an accretion disc, whose constituent matter spins around the black hole to fractions of the speed of light. The disc emits light. This is what has enabled the Event Horizon Telescope Collaboration to obtain in 2019 the first image of a black hole, or more precisely the first image of a black hole accretion disc (see cover).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study carried out during this internship concerns the modelling of radiation signature of matter near black hole, similar to that of M87* observed in 2019. To study a black hole theoretically, the most suitable tool is general relativity, considering gravity as a reason for deformation of space time. The framework used to study a massive, non-rotating spherical object is the Schwarzschild metric, which characterises the deformation of space-time caused by such an object. The light emanating from the accretion disc follows a trajectory to reach the observer. These paths are not simply straights lines as in the limit of flat space-time, but are curved and constitute geodesic lines. Calculation of photon paths can be done exactly via ray tracing, or  approximately via analytical methods. We thus obtain the image of the accretion disc perceived from different inclinations, by an observer placed at infinity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Light can be considered as an electromagnetic wave, oscillating through space. For different photons, the electric field differs, but if there is a preferred direction, the light is polarized. This is subject to the effects of special and general relativity. Thus the polarisation of the light emitted by the fluid constituting the accretion disc is not the same as that measured by the observer. By using basis changes, we were able to obtain the polarisation angle measured in the observer&amp;rsquo;s sky.
By first approximating an infinitely thin accretion disc, then with a non-zero thickness, we were able to obtain an image of an accretion disc around black hole, as well as the degree and angle of polarisation at each point.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
