<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Particle Physics | Matthieu Pelissier</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/particle-physics/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/particle-physics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Particle Physics</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 02 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://localhost:1313/media/icon_hu7729264130191091259.png</url>
      <title>Particle Physics</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/particle-physics/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Solving a differential equation for calibration of the ATLAS detector via a neural networks.</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/project/atlas/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/project/atlas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/project/atlas/distribution.jpg&#34;
    alt=&#34;Calibration Example: using neural network solution for ODE-based calibration function&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Calibration Example: using neural network solution for ODE-based calibration function&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Supervisor :&lt;/strong&gt; Pierre-Antoine Delsart, lecturer, ATLAS, LPSC, France.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results of this internship have been presented in a &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/event/altasworkshop/&#34;&gt;workshop of the collaboration&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The particle physics studied at the LHC by the ATLAS detector requires high-precision measurements.
precision. The energy quantities associated with hadronic jet objects cannot be used directly from experimental measurements, and must be corrected in order to be compared with theoretical predictions.
from experimental measurements, and must be corrected before they can be compared with theoretical predictions. This addresses this problem in the form of a nonlinear second-order differential equation on the calibration function
function, which has no analytical solution. A neural network is used to solve it. The aim is to
is to obtain an accurate calibration function by exploiting the non-linear capabilities of neural networks.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quantum states of neutrons in a gravitational field</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/project/gravity/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/project/gravity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Supervisor :&lt;/strong&gt;  Benoit Chalopin, lecturer, LCAR, Paul Sabatier University, Toulouse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many fields of physics, when studying the motion of a particle at the microscopic scale, the gravitational interaction is led to be neglected in front of other interactions such as the electromagnetic interaction, or at shorter range the strong and weak interactions. Indeed, if we focus on the interactions between  the proton and the electron forming a hydrogen atom, we can show that
the gravitational interaction is 1040 times less than the electromagnetic interaction. However, at this scale, gravity can imply a quantum behavior that we have presented.
During this presentation, we have approached the problem from a theoretical point of view before considering an experimental approach established by the GRANIT experiment.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
